<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at St. Mary-le-Bow to the Societies for Reformation of Manners, April 5, 1697 by Lilly Butler.</title>
            <author>Butler, Lilly.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30733</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27140</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09674122</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09674122</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43952</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30733)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43952)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1326:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at St. Mary-le-Bow to the Societies for Reformation of Manners, April 5, 1697 by Lilly Butler.</title>
                  <author>Butler, Lilly.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for B. Aylmer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Galatians IV, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43952:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43952:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A SERMON Preach'd at <hi>St. Mary-le-Bow,</hi> TO THE <hi>SOCIETIES</hi> FOR Reformation of Manners, <hi>April</hi> 5. 1697.</p>
            <p>By <hi>LILLY B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TLER</hi> Miniſter of St. <hi>Mary Aldermanbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>B. Aylmer</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1697. Price 4 d.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43952:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:43952:2"/>
            <head>TO THE SOCIETIES FOR <hi>Reformation of MANNERS</hi> In the Cities of <hi>London</hi> &amp; <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have yielded to your Requeſt for the Publiſhing of this Sermon, though I cannot but expect to undergo ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>favourable Cenſures for it. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and Profeſſed Enemies of that Cauſe it pleads, will undoubtedly, if it come in their way, be very liberal of their ſilly Scoffs, and foul Reproaches: But ſuch Dirt is not worthy of any other regard, but to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed and trampled on. I am only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned for the Cenſures of ſome better Men,
<pb facs="tcp:43952:3"/> who perhaps, through ſome falſe Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of you and your Proceedings, may condemn that encouragement I have given to your Zeal and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakings. I ſhall therefore take this opportunity to acquaint them, that, after very curious inquiries into theſe matters, and a deliberate conſulting with my own Conſcience, I thought it high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly became me to ſpeak, what I have here Publiſhed. They that were Inveſted with the Legiſlative Power, did judg it very neceſſary to make divers Laws, for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing ſome Common and Scandalous Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to ſhame and puniſhment. And our late <hi>Gracious Queen,</hi> of Bleſſed Memory, was pleaſed to give her particular Injunction, to thoſe whoſe proper Buſineſs it was, to put theſe Laws in execution. Bleſſed be God, we have ſome Magiſtrates, who are very ready to diſcharge their Duty in this matter. But they cannot exerciſe that Power, is given them by God and the King, of making the <hi>Sword</hi> in their Hands an effectual <hi>Terror to evil doers,</hi> without evidence and conviction. And for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing of theſe, it lies upon Private Perſons to aſſiſt them. If therefore any Good be to
<pb facs="tcp:43952:3"/> be done, by the execution of Laws, they are in a great Meaſure anſwerable for it, if it be not effected.</p>
            <p>There is need of a great deal of <hi>Zeal</hi> for God and Religion, to give Men the courage to ingage heartily in a work, which muſt Expoſe them to ſuch great Expences, ſuch ſevere Cenſures, ſuch bitter Revilings, and ſuch mighty Oppoſition, as they, who have been employed in proſecuting this affair, have had abundant Experience of. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, having undertaken to preach upon this Occaſion, I endeavoured to ſpeak ſomething in Vindication, and for the further incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of your Zeal in ſo <hi>good a Thing.</hi> But knowing very well, that <hi>Zeal,</hi> in the beſt Matters, may eaſily tranſport men beyond what is fit, and really ſerviceable to the End it would promote, I thought it my Duty to give you ſome Cautions and Directions for the Management of it. And I hope this part of my diſcourſe was not the leaſt acceptable to you. Thus far alſo, I believe, I may promiſe for you, that, if any Good Men will be ſo kind, as to add their Advice for the due and effectual ordering of your endeavours, for the reforming or reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:43952:4"/> the abominable Vices of the Age, you will thankfully accept and readily follow it. And, I conceive, it will not become any Men, raſhly to condemn your Proceedings in ſo good a deſign, till they are well aſſured, that your Methods are faulty, and their better Counſels are rejected.</p>
            <p>It is certainly <hi>a good thing</hi> you profeſs to be <hi>Zealouſly affected in,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo far your Zeal muſt be <hi>good</hi> too. But your great care ſhould be that it may be as good in all other Circumſtances, as it is in reſpect of its End and Object: That it be not Biaſſed by any partial reſpects, or led out of its way by any raſh or indiſcreet Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels; that it be always attended with a holy and irreproveable Converſation, and adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the greateſt Modeſty and Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. This would be the moſt Effectual courſe, <hi>to put to Silence the Ignorance of Fooliſh,</hi> and the Malice of Wicked <hi>Men;</hi> and to ingage the Affection and Aſſiſtance of all Good Men. And I hope, theſe are not ſo Inconſiderable a party, as to be eaſily overcome in their uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted endeavours for God and Religon, whilſt they have the Laws of the Land, both to
<pb facs="tcp:43952:4"/> defend themſelves, and to oppoſe their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies with. A Frown, or a hard Word, are generally the worst things we have to Fear. Where then is our love to God or our Country, if we have not Courage enough, in a Cauſe wherein they are ſo much concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to bear up againſt ſuch weak, contemptible Aſſaults? Oh! that we might but ſee all ſorts of good Men, Magiſtrates, Miniſters and others, all conſpiring together to make one Bold and vigorous Effort, for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing thoſe publick and ſcandalous Vices, which cry ſo loud to Heaven againſt us. We could have little cauſe to Deſpair of the Good Succeſs of ſuch a truly Religious <hi>Aſſociation.</hi> I am glad to underſtand there is ſuch a hopeful proſpect of it, from that great addition of new Bodies of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables and Houſekeepers and others, who, within a few Months paſt, have united to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for the diſcharge of their Oaths and Conſciences in this particular; and from the great Incouragement they have from the Government of this City. And I hope it will pleaſe God, to diſpoſe the hearts of our Magiſtrates, in other parts of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſo to conſider the Oaths they have
<pb facs="tcp:43952:5"/> taken, and the account they muſt give to God, of the exerciſe of that Power and Authority they are inveſted with; that they may not dare to ſuffer any private Conſiderations, to hold their hands from that execution of Laws, wherein the glory of God and the publick Good are ſo much concerned. We <hi>know the Terrour of the Lord,</hi> and <hi>therefore</hi> cannot but ſpeak, and with the greatest Zeal and Compaſſion, <hi>endeavour to perſuade Men,</hi> to a faithful perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of thoſe Duties, which are of ſuch mighty Importance to us all, both with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to our preſent and everlaſting Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs.</p>
            <p>You have the Honour to lead in this Noble Deſign, and if you reſolutely and wiſely Proceed in your endeavours for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing of it, you may Reaſonably hope to provoke others by your Zeal and Succeſs, to joyn their Heads, and Hearts, and Hands with you. However you may be ſure, that God <hi>will not forget your Works of Faith, and labours of Love, and patience of Hope;</hi> but render unto you according to the Zeal, and Integrity, and Constancy of your endeavours for him. <hi>Caſt not away</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:43952:5"/> 
               <hi>therefore your confidence, which hath ſo great a recompence of reward. Deal courageouſly, and the Lord will be with the Good;</hi> If not to render your Attempts ſucceſsful, yet certainly to ſupport and comfort you in them, and to Bleſs and Reward you for them. That you may happily experience the preſence of God with you, for all theſe good ends and purpoſes, <hi>is the hearty Prayer of,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your affectionate Friend and Servant <hi>LILLY BUTLER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43952:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:43952:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:43952:7"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43952:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Gal. iv. 18.</bibl>
               <q>It is good to be zealouſly affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed always in a good thing.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE deſign of our aſſembling together at this time, and in this manner, is to vindicate and encourage the moſt <hi>zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> endeavours to reform the Vices of the Age, and particularly, by helping forward the execution of our <hi>good</hi> Laws upon <hi>evil</hi> Men, upon notorious and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Tranſgreſſors. I ſhall therefore conſider, how much ſuch Practices as theſe are Warranted and Recommended to us, by that general account <hi>St. Paul</hi> gives of the proper Objects of our Zeal, and the Excellency of it when it hath reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to ſuch Objects, in the words of the <hi>Text, It is good to be zealouſly affected always in a good thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:43952:8"/>
            <p> That I may make this Diſcourſe then as Serviceable as I can to the End for which it is intended, I ſhall do theſe following things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt.</hi> I ſhall ſhew, That endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in our ſeveral places, to reform the corrupt Manners of the Age we live in, is a <hi>good</hi> work, and therefore proper mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be <hi>zealous in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> I ſhall ſhew, That to help forward the execution of Penal Laws, upon notorious and ſcandalous Sinners, is a <hi>good</hi> work, and therefore alſo proper matter to be <hi>zealous in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly.</hi> I ſhall ſhew, What it is to <hi>be zealouſly affected in</hi> theſe or any <hi>good things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly.</hi> I ſhall ſhew, What are to be the qualifications of our <hi>Zeal</hi> in theſe things, or what cautions are to be given to them that are thus <hi>zealouſly affected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly.</hi> I ſhall anſwer ſome Objections againſt our being thus <hi>zealouſly affected in</hi> theſe matters. And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly.</hi> I ſhall direct to ſome proper Conſiderations, for the <hi>affecting</hi> our hearts with <hi>Zeal in theſe good things.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43952:8"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> I am to ſhew, That endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our ſeveral places, to reform the corrupt Manners of the Age we live in, is a <hi>good</hi> work, and therefore proper mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be <hi>zealous in.</hi> It is endeavouring to do thoſe things, which beſt become, and moſt behove us to do; by which the moſt excellent purpoſes are ſerved, and the higheſt obligations anſwered; and therefore it muſt be one of the beſt works we can be ingaged in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> It is endeavouring to advance the honour of God, which indeed ought to be the end of all our endeavours. It is the end for which we have our being; for which all our Time, and all our Powers, and Faculties were given us. And what can be done more for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, than reforming the lives of Men? When Men are reformed, then they proclaim, not only with their Lips but in their Lives, their acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Sovereign Majeſty and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, of his moſt excellent Perfections, of the Goodneſs and Equity of his Laws, of the Wiſdom and Juſtice of his Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations: Then they reverence his Name,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43952:9"/> and fear his Power, and love his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and truſt in his Promiſes, and give him that veneration and worſhip is due to him: Then they <hi>ſhew forth his Virtues,</hi> and manifeſt the <hi>Power of his Grace;</hi> and, by the continual exerciſe of Love and Charity, do <hi>cauſe abundant Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings unto God.</hi> This is Honouring of God indeed, of God our Maker and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver, our greateſt Friend and Benefactor, of our infinitely great and good God. What better imployment then can we have, more our Duty or more our Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, than endeavouring to increaſe the Number of thoſe by whom he is thus Glorified? How can we <hi>Love God,</hi> in any ſenſe, <hi>with all our Heart, and with all our Mind, and with all our Strength,</hi> if we do not proſecute ſuch Deſigns, with the utmoſt warmth and vigour of all our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly.</hi> This is endeavouring to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the Honour and Intereſt of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity. And ſurely this is always <hi>good,</hi> but was never more neceſſary than Now. What can <hi>adorn the Doctrin of our God and Saviour,</hi> like the Holy Lives of its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors?
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43952:9"/> How would the Truth and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence, the Power and Efficacy of our Religion be Demonſtrated, when it ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued the unruly Paſſions, mortified the ſtrongeſt Luſts, conquered the moſt ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Temptations, extirpated the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterate Habits of Sin, and adorned us with all the Beauties of a Chriſtian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation? Who could forbear to love, and admire, and acknowledge the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of that Revelation, which brought forth ſuch excellent Fruit; ſo worthy of God, ſo <hi>good and Profitable unto Men?</hi> Not all the Arguments of <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels,</hi> have done that Miſchief to <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity,</hi> as the lewd and diſſolute Lives of its Profeſſors. And we can never hope to ſee it recover the Reputation it hath loſt, and overcome the powerful Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is now made againſt it, till we have better Lives to plead for it. What then can more deſerve our <hi>Zeal,</hi> than the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting that Reformation, which is ſo neceſſary and ſo prevailing a Means, to vindicate the Truth and Honour of that Religion, our <hi>Bleſſed Lord and Saviour</hi> came down from Heaven to Reveal, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43952:10"/> died upon the Croſs to bear Witneſs to?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly.</hi> This is endeavouring, in the beſt, and moſt effectual manner we can, to promote the Publick good of our Country. It is from our ſcandalous Vices, that moſt of our publick Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Spring, in a Natural way, and by theſe that the Wrath of God is provoked. And how can we do better Service to our Country, than by concurring to ſtop that raging Peſtilence of Sin, which is ready to overſpread the Land; and to carry Infection, and Death, and Miſery into every corner of it; to ſet our ſelves <hi>in the gap,</hi> to keep out that inundation of Wrath which is breaking in upon us; to help to reſtore that <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> which <hi>Exalts a Nation,</hi> which is the Honour and Safety of a People; which endears them to God, unites them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, baniſhes thoſe Vices to which publick miſchiefs and grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are owing, and makes every Man a Hearty Friend to his Neighbour and the common good? What imployment then can better deſerve our <hi>Zeal,</hi> than endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring that Reformation of the lives of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43952:10"/> Men, which would more conduce to make us a flouriſhing and happy People, than all other our wiſeſt Counſels, our ſtrongeſt Armies, and our moſt liberal expence of Treaſure and Blood?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly.</hi> It is endeavouring to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the particular good of our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, in every valuable reſpect. It is endeavouring to propagate that <hi>Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> which <hi>is profitable unto all things, having the Promiſe of the Life that now is, and of that which is to come.</hi> It is endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to reclaim Men from thoſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Luſts and practices, which impair their Health, and waſt their Eſtates, and blemiſh their Reputation, and wound their Conſciences, and <hi>War againſt their Souls,</hi> and ſink them down into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Perdition. It is endeavouring to reſtore Men to the favour and likeneſs of God; to bring them into the <hi>Peaceable</hi> and <hi>Pleaſant Paths</hi> of Righteouſneſs; to reſcue them <hi>from the Bondage of Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into the glorious liberty of the Sons of God;</hi> to ſecure to them a comfortable Life, a hopeful Death, and a bleſſed Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality. Certainly ſuch Generous,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43952:11"/> ſuch Charitable, ſuch Beneficial endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, cannot but be exceeding <hi>good</hi> and worthy of our utmoſt <hi>Zeal</hi> and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour. Thus much may ſuffice to ſhew, the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of our Endeavours in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, for reforming the evil Lives of Men. I proceed now,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly.</hi> To ſhew, That to help for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the execution of Penal Laws, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on notorious and ſcandalous Sinners, is a <hi>good</hi> Work, and therefore alſo proper matter to be <hi>zealous in.</hi> This will be manifeſt if we conſider,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> How much the execution of Penal Laws, would conduce to that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Manners, which, I have already ſhewed, ſo eminently promotes the Honour of God, the Intereſt of Chriſtianity, the Welfare of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and the preſent and eternal Good and Happineſs of Men. It muſt needs be a great Diſcouragement to Vice, to ſee it continually expoſing Men to Shame and Puniſhment; to ſee Men of Honour and Authority imployed againſt it. Piety and Virtue muſt needs gather Strength and Boldneſs, when the Sword
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43952:11"/> of Juſtice defends them, and chaſtiſeth the Enemies of them: When Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is forced to hide its Head, and to creep into Corners, for Fear of it. The Habits of Sin will loſe their ſtrength, when they are reſtrained from exerciſe; and it cannot ſpread its Infection ſo wide, when the Examples of it are not ſuffered to be Common, Publick, or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure; when it is forced out of current uſe and Faſhion: When Men cannot combine, in ſuch Numbers, for the practice and Countenance of it, to aid and hearten one another in it. The ſins of the Nation then would certainly be leſs in Number, leſs Scandalous, and leſs Provoking. If the execution of Laws could effect no more than this, yet God would be nothing ſo much diſhonoured, nor our Religion diſgraced, nor the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Danger of publick Judgments, and therefore it cannot but be a <hi>Good thing,</hi> and great enough to deſerve our moſt warm and vigorous Endeavours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly.</hi> Such an execution of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Juſtice, though it ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail but little towards the Reforming of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43952:12"/> Men, yet it might, for its own ſake, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure many Bleſſings from God to a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The Actions of publick Perſons, in their publick Stations, have the greateſt Influence upon the publick good. Theſe are the Actions of the Society, and therefore will the ſooneſt procure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Judgments or Bleſſings. For Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and Magiſtracy, and the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Juſtice, belong to a Society as ſuch; and therefore, according as theſe are adminiſtred, it is reaſonable to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect God ſhould diſpenſe his publick Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours. It was for want of <hi>Eli</hi>'s execut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Judgment upon his lewd <hi>Sons,</hi> that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were delivered into the Hands of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and the <hi>Ark of God taken</hi> from them. 'Till Judgment was executed upon <hi>Achan</hi> for <hi>the Accurſed thing,</hi> the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſtill fled before their Enemies. It was by <hi>executing Judgment</hi> upon two ſcandalous Offenders, that <hi>Phinehas</hi> ſtayed the fury of a devouring Plague, and <hi>restored health to the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Iſrael.</hi> Such another might af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards have ſaved them from Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; <hi>if</hi> they could have <hi>found a Man in</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:43952:12"/> 
                  <hi>Jeruſalem that executed Judgment,</hi> God would have <hi>Pardoned it,</hi> Jer. 5. 1. But Magiſtrates cannot ordinarily do this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, if there be none to teſtify againſt the Tranſgreſſors. It is <hi>good</hi> therefore for us all, in our ſeveral places, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the promoting ſo <hi>good</hi> a Work. As Magiſtrates ſhould be forward to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute Judgment, ſo ſhould others be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to diſcover and accuſe notorious Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, without which there would be no opportunity for it. Theſe are <hi>good things</hi> then, I have been hitherto plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for, and therefore ſuch as we ought <hi>to be zealouſly affected in.</hi> I proceed now,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly.</hi> To ſhew, What it is <hi>to be zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly affected in a good</hi> matter, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently what is our Duty, with reſpect to thoſe exceeding <hi>good</hi> matters, which are under our preſent conſideration. <hi>Zeal</hi> is the warmth and fervency of the Soul and Spirit, that which actuates all our Powers and Faculties, and inſpires them with a new life and vigour, in the purſuit of that we are zealous for. More particularly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> He that is <hi>zealouſly affected</hi> in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43952:13"/> any matter, will be very earneſt in his deſires of ſucceeding in it. He will wiſh and long for more Power, and greater Opportunities, and ſtronger Aids, for the accompliſhing of it. His Thoughts will be mighty intent upon it; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually buſied, in ſeeking out proper and effectual ways of proſpering in his Endeavours for it. He will follow it with as vehement Deſires, as covetous and ambitious Men do Riches and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Where then is our Zeal for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, that moſt excellent good Thing, if we ſeldom think how we may be ſerviceable to the promoting of it; If we are not grieved that we can do no more towards it; If we careleſly neglect any proper means or opportunities of being aiding and aſſiſting to it; If we willingly ſhift it off to others, and are glad to be excuſed from having any hand in it our ſelves? It is very ſad to think of it, but this, I fear, is almoſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Caſe of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> of thoſe I mean that call themſelves ſo: For what can they have of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> beſides the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of it, who are thus coldly <hi>affected</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:43952:13"/> to that, wherein the Honour of <hi>Christ</hi> and his Goſpel, and the Happineſs of thoſe, for whom he was born and died, are ſo very much concerned?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly.</hi> He that is <hi>zealouſly affected</hi> to any <hi>good</hi> End, will be exceeding active and induſtrious in the proſecution of it. His Endeavours will be proportionable to his Deſires, great and ſtrong as they. Such was the Zeal of our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> who <hi>went about doing good;</hi> and that of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which engaged him <hi>in Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings often, and in Labours more abundant.</hi> And if we are <hi>zealouſly affected</hi> towards the reforming the lives of Men, we ſhall not be <hi>ſlothful in</hi> this <hi>Buſineſs, but fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent in Spirit, ſerving the Lord</hi> with all our Might in it. We ſhall never think we can take too much pains, or grudge any toil or labour for the accompliſhing of it. When an Opportunity appears to us, we ſhall greedily embrace it, and improve it with our utmoſt Vigour. Where then is our <hi>Zeal in</hi> this matter? What little Difficulties diſcourage us? How little Time or Pains do we imploy in it? How much ſhort do the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43952:14"/> of us come, of the reſtleſs tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, and unwearied diligence, with which we ſee Men every day labouring, for the uncertain Riches, the fading Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and the vain and forbidden Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this world?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly.</hi> He that is <hi>zealouſly affected</hi> in any <hi>good thing,</hi> will be very courage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the purſuit of it. If we were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>zealouſly affected</hi> to this good work of reforming the Lives of Men, we ſhould not eaſily be frighted from doing our part in it, by the Enemies and Oppoſition we are like to encounter with. We ſhould not care, what a fooliſh World may call us, or how a malicious World may uſe us. We ſhould <hi>not be afraid of their Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours,</hi> or diſcouraged by their Cenſures, or put out of countenance by their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, but boldly and reſolutely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in that <hi>Good</hi> Cauſe we are ingaged in. Theſe would be but as dry <hi>Hay and Stubble,</hi> unable to ſtop the progreſs of a flaming <hi>Zeal</hi> for God and Religion; we ſhould ſcorn to deſert ſo pious, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and profitable a Work, for fear of thoſe ſilly, and lewd, and ungodly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43952:14"/> Wretches that oppoſe it. We ſhould <hi>go out in the name of the Lord</hi> againſt them, and <hi>in that have ſtrong confidence.</hi> Though we knew that we muſt <hi>wrestle, both with Fleſh and Blood, and with ſpiritual wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes in high Places,</hi> yet for all this we ſhould not decline the Combate, but <hi>be ſtrong in the Lord and in the power of his Might.</hi> We ſhould be ready to anſwer with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> if we were told as he was, that <hi>bonds and afflictions</hi> did <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide us,</hi> that <hi>none of theſe things move us, neither count we our lives dear unto us, ſo that Chriſt may be magnified in our Bodies, Acts</hi> 20. 23, 24. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 20. The oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition we meet with would rather heigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten our Courage, and ſtrengthen our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, and animate our Endeavours, and increaſe our Labours, in ſo pious and charitable a Work.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly.</hi> He that is <hi>zealouſly affected in a good thing,</hi> will be liberal in his Expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the promoting of it. Thus we find the <hi>Zeal</hi> of the Primitive <hi>Chriſtians</hi> prevailed with them, even to <hi>ſell their poſſeſſions, and to lay the price at the Apoſtles feet,</hi> when the great Neceſſities of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43952:15"/> Church required it of them, <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 34, 35. Thus alſo the <hi>Zeal</hi> of the <hi>Churches of Macedonia,</hi> made <hi>the riches of their liberality to abound, in their deep poverty;</hi> They <hi>were ready,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>to their</hi> power, <hi>yea and beyond their power, they were willing of themſelves, praying us with much intreaty, that we would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Gift,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 3, 4. They offered more unasked, than they could well ſpare, and earneſtly beſought them to accept their Contributions. Thus libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſhould we be in advancing thoſe <hi>good</hi> works we are pleading for, if we were as <hi>zealouſly affected</hi> as they were. We ſhould be <hi>glad to distribute, and willing to communicate</hi> of our earthly Goods, in ſo heavenly a Cauſe, ſo acceptable to God, ſo ſerviceable to his Honour and to the Intereſt of his Church and Kingdom. But becauſe as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> intimates, in the Verſe before the <hi>Text,</hi> we may be <hi>zealouſly affected, but not well.</hi> I proceed,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly.</hi> To ſhew, what are to be the Qualifications of our <hi>Zeal</hi> in theſe things; or what Cautions are to be given to them, whoare thus <hi>zealouſly affected.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:43952:15"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> Our Zeal muſt be impartial with reſpect to Perſons and Parties. It is a general <hi>Reformation</hi> of all ſorts of Men we pretend to be <hi>zealous</hi> for; and therefore it muſt not have only a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Regard to ſome particular Men. The Laws are made for the reſtraint, and correction of all Mens enormous Vices, and therefore our Endeavours, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the execution of them, ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo have equal Reſpect to all. God and Religion are diſhonoured, and the Publick good is prejudiced and indangered, by all ſorts of wicked Men, and all Mens Souls are equally hazarded by their ſcandalous Offences. And therefore it cannot be a truly religious Zeal, which is guided by any private or partial Reſpects. It may be a <hi>Zeal</hi> of Spight and Malice, of ſome carnal or worldly Affection; but it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a <hi>Zeal</hi> of Love to God and our Neighbour. If it were a <hi>Zeal</hi> of Love to God, it would uſe the ſame Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, where the Honour of God is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually concerned; if it were a Zeal of Love to our Neighbour, it would not be leaſt active, where we love moſt. If
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43952:16"/> we uſe thoſe we call the Means of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and promote the execution of Laws, chiefly upon thoſe, to whoſe Perſons, or Intereſts, or religious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion we are diſaffected; our pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Zeal,</hi> for a general Reformation of Mens Lives, is certainly counterfeit and hypocritical. It cannot be thought, we ſhould be moſt concerned for their good, for whom we have the leaſt Affection. And therefore the <hi>Zeal</hi> of ſuch Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, will ſhew a great concern to ſee Men puniſhed rather than reformed. It will not be puniſhing Mens Perſons, that we may reform their Vices; but puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Vices, that we may hurt their Perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly.</hi> Our <hi>Zeal</hi> muſt be wiſe and prudent, and all its Endeavours guided with Deliberation and Diſcretion. <hi>Zeal</hi> is a ſharp Inſtrument, and therefore not to be managed with a careleſs or unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Hand. If we uſe it raſhly, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good Advice, we may ſtab our own Deſigns, and ruin that Cauſe we would defend by it. We ſhould <hi>not</hi> therefore <hi>lean</hi> too much <hi>to our own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings,</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:43952:16"/> in the methods of proſecuting thoſe <hi>good</hi> Deſigns we are <hi>zealous in:</hi> but be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually <hi>asking Counſel of God,</hi> and of grave, and wiſe, and experienced Men. We ſhould conſider Seaſons and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and, with great Deliberation and Judgment, make choice of thoſe that are moſt proper, to ſet forward the good Work we have in hand. In pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the noble deſign of <hi>Reformation,</hi> wherein you are like to meet with ſo many Difficulties, and ſuch mighty Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, it will behove you, as wiſe Men are wont to do in like caſes, to ſtrengthen your Hands all you can, to unite your Forces, and to combine toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into <hi>Societies;</hi> that you may mutual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adviſe, and countenance, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and encourage, and vindicate, and defend one another, in your Attempts for the Accompliſhing of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly.</hi> Your <hi>Zeal</hi> muſt be orderly. It muſt not tranſport you beyond the Bounds of your Places and Callings. Private perſons muſt not uſurp the Office of the Prieſt or Magiſtrate; but move ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly in their own Sphere, towards that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43952:17"/> good End they have before them. <hi>God hath ſet us in the Church as Members in the Body,</hi> and <hi>all Members have not the ſame Office;</hi> If the Feet will invade the Office of the Head, what can follow but over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning and confuſion? <hi>The Law is good if we uſe it lawfully:</hi> But if we deſert our Station, or take any illegal courſes to procure the execution of it, we make our ſelves Tranſgreſſors, whilſt we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be <hi>Reformers.</hi> We cannot expect the Countenance of ſober Men, or the Protection and Bleſſing of God. You know how ſeverely God dealt with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>z<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zah,</hi> for his irregular <hi>Zeal,</hi> in attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to preſerve the <hi>Ark of God</hi> from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly.</hi> Your Zeal in theſe <hi>good</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, muſt be, attended with a proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable regard to all other parts of your Duty, and of the ſame Piece with the reſt of your Lives; otherwiſe it will very ill become you, and ſerve the End it is in perſuit of. You muſt <hi>be holy, and harmleſs,</hi> and <hi>without rebuke</hi> your ſelves, whilſt you are zealouſly endeavouring to reform the Vices of <hi>a crooked and perverſe</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:43952:17"/> 
                  <hi>Nation.</hi> You may reaſonably expect that reply, <hi>Phyſician heal thy ſelf,</hi> when you are applying Remedies to other Mens Diſeaſes, and are infected with thoſe that are as mortal your ſelves. You muſt carefully avoid <hi>giving</hi> any juſt <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion</hi> to any man <hi>to ſpeak evil of you,</hi> for many will ſeek Occaſions, and improve them all they can, to diſgrace both you and the <hi>good</hi> Deſign you are <hi>zealouſly affected in.</hi> But if whilſt you make Men feel the Warmth of your <hi>Zeal,</hi> they alſo <hi>ſee</hi> the <hi>Light of</hi> it <hi>ſhine before them,</hi> in all the exerciſes of <hi>a ſober, righteous, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> life; this will be ſuch a manifeſt Proof of the Sincerity of its intentions, to ſerve God and to do good, as <hi>none of its adverſaries will be able to gainſay or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt.</hi> Then Men will be aſhamed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach it, or to impute the Endeavours of it, to any corrupt Affections, or to any worldly ſiniſter Ends. Then no good man will be aſhamed to appear for you, to plead your Cauſe, or to encourage your Endeavours. Then you may rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably hope, that God will not throw you aſide, as unworthy Inſtruments for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43952:18"/> ſuch noble Purpoſes; but be ready to aſſiſt, and bleſs, and proſper your Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings for him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly.</hi> Your <hi>Zeal</hi> ſhould be attended with great Humility, with low thoughts of your ſelves and your beſt perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, and a modeſt and humble Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour towards all Men; for Pride and Selfe-conceit will ſtain the Beauty, and hinder the Efficacy, of the moſt zealous Endeavours for God and Religion. Theſe are Vices, that are <hi>abominable</hi> both <hi>in the ſight of God</hi> and Man, and corrupt every thing that hath relation to them. And theſe are the Sins you will be moſt in danger of. For this is the common Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem, whereby the <hi>Devil</hi> overcomes ſuch, as have held out againſt all his other Temptations. He endeavours to flatter them into a great Opinion of their own Virtue, and to make them proud of their Conqueſts over him; and ſo ſecures them to himſelf, by magnifying the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice they have done againſt him. Let this then be your particular care, to arm your ſelves againſt this Temptation, and to keep your Zeal always <hi>cloathed with</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:43952:18"/> 
                  <hi>Humility,</hi> which will be the greateſt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament you can give it. Be as thankful as you can for it, but never make it your Boaſt, that you <hi>are not as other Men are.</hi> Conſider then, who it is that <hi>makes you to differ,</hi> and of <hi>whoſe only gift it comes</hi> that you are able <hi>to do unto God any good and laudable Service;</hi> that every good Work you do, increaſeth your obligation to do more for him, but can be no juſt reaſon for your <hi>thinking more highly of your ſelves;</hi> that when you have done the moſt and beſt you can for him, you are far from <hi>rendring unto him according to all he hath done for you;</hi> and have ſtill reaſon to hold down your Heads, and to ſmite upon your Breaſts and ſay, every one of you, <hi>God be Merciful unto me a Sinner.</hi> You have an excellent Example of this <hi>Zeal</hi> and Humility together in St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who <hi>laboured more abundantly than they all,</hi> yet he calls himſelf the <hi>leaſt of the Apoſtles,</hi> and gives all the Glory to God, <hi>It was not I,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>but the Grace of God that was with me.</hi> I come now</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:43952:19"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Fifthly.</hi> To anſwer ſome Objections, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our <hi>zealous</hi> Endeavours to reform the Vices of the Age.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> Some are ready to object, that this is not a proper Seaſon for ſuch At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts. Wickedneſs is ſo impudent and daring, and ſo much countenanced by thoſe, who are moſt able and obliged to ſuppreſs it, that now to conteſt zealouſly againſt it, is but <hi>labouring in vain, and ſpending our Strength for nought,</hi> and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make it inſult and triumph the more, upon baffling our Endeavours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. There is indeed but too much Truth in this Character of the Age we live in; but however, it ought not to quench our <hi>Zeal</hi> in labouring to make it better. For.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> We find the holy Servants of God were not diſcouraged, in former times, by the ſame Difficulties. When <hi>all fleſh had corrupted themſelves</hi> Noah <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued</hi> a zealous <hi>Preacher of Righteouſneſs.</hi> When the <hi>Cry</hi> of <hi>Sodom</hi>'s <hi>ſins was gone up to Heaven,</hi> and they were moſt impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently bold in their commiſſion of them, <hi>righteous Lot</hi> did not ceaſe to rebuke and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43952:19"/> oppoſe their Wickedneſs. When <hi>the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars of God were throwing down,</hi> and the People were ſlaying his <hi>Prophets,</hi> even then was <hi>Elijah exceeding Jealous for the Lord God of Hoſts.</hi> The Holy <hi>Prophets</hi> did zealouſly ſet themſelves to reform the Manners, <hi>of a ſinful</hi> Nation, <hi>a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple laden with iniquity,</hi> and inraged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all that oppoſed their growing Wickedneſs. <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> did not forbear his warnings and reproofs, when he was beſet with a <hi>Generation of Vipers.</hi> And the Bleſſed <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> with undaunted Courage, perſiſted to defend the Cauſe of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> when <hi>it was every where ſpoken againſt.</hi> Were not theſe Men of <hi>like Paſſions with our ſelves?</hi> Is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the Lives of Men as good a Work as ever? Have we not the ſame God to aſſiſt us, the ſame Laws to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige us, and the ſame Reward to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage us, that they had? What Excuſe can we find in the difficulty of this Work now, which they might not have pleaded for laying aſide that Zeal, with which they endeavoured the accompliſhing of it? But</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:43952:20"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Secondly.</hi> The worſe the Age is, the more <hi>zealous</hi> ſhould the Friends of Pietie and Virtue be to make it better. When we ſee Religion almoſt ready to expire, where is our Love to God or that, if we do not haſten to its relief, and apply our moſt earneſt Endeavours for the ſupport and recovery of it? When that is loſt, then all our Hopes are loſt; then there will <hi>nothing remain for</hi> us, <hi>but a fearful looking for of Judgment and fiery Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to devour</hi> us. And can any Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties excuſe our Sloth, when the Danger is ſo great and ſo apparent? When Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is almoſt irrecoverably oppreſt, and cries with dying Groans for ſuccour, ſhall we refuſe to fly to its Defence, for fear we ſhould indanger it by our Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance? What a brave and noble thing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would it be, to encounter Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the height of all its Triumphs, to <hi>go out in the Name of the Lord</hi> againſt it, when it prides its ſelf in its Gyant-like ſtature, and hath all its Weapons of War about it, and moſt inſolently <hi>defies the Armies of the living God?</hi> How would ſuch Zeal and Courage become the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43952:20"/> Chidren of the <hi>Lord of Hoſts,</hi> their noble birth, and <hi>high calling,</hi> and glorious hopes and expectations?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly.</hi> As bad as the Age is, we have no reaſon utterly to deſpair of all Succeſs, in theſe our <hi>zealous</hi> Attempts to amend it. It is the Cauſe of God, a Cauſe wherein his Honour is mightily concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, a Cauſe he loves to ſee us ingaged in, a Cauſe in which he hath oftentimes wonderfully aſſiſted, a Cauſe he ſeems not to have caſt off all regard to at this time amongſt us. We have great reaſon to think <hi>it is of God,</hi> that, amidſt ſo many Diſcouragements, it hath come into the Hearts of ſome to unite their <hi>zealous</hi> Endeavours, to repreſs the Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of inſulting Wickedneſs, and to reſcue Pietie and Religion from that Contempt and Oppreſſion it labours un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Who knows, but that <hi>little Cloud,</hi> which appears but <hi>as a Mans Hand,</hi> may, by the Bleſſing of God, ſo improve and ſpread its ſelf, as to be able at length by its refreſhing Showers, to renew the life, and ſtrength, and beauty, of withering Virtue. The <hi>Powers of Darkneſs,</hi> and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43952:21"/> the corrupt Nature of Man are againſt us; but, <hi>if God be for us,</hi> we are certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſtronger ſide. And why ſhould we not hope, that God will at length <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe and plead his own Cauſe,</hi> and <hi>make his Work proſper in the Hands</hi> of thoſe, that faithfully and zealouſly apply themſelves <hi>to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty?</hi> For <hi>the Eyes of the Lord run to and fro throughout the whole Earth, to ſhew himſelf ſtrong in the behalf of them, whoſe Heart is perfect towards Him,</hi> 2. Chron. 16. 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly.</hi> How unſuccesful ſoever our <hi>zealous</hi> Endeavours may be for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the Nation, yet they may be ſuccesful for the Preſervation and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of it. God may ſhew Favour to the whole Body, for the ſake of thoſe few Members of it, that are ingaged ſo heartily in promoting his Honour and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. He may do that for us for their ſakes, which he did for <hi>Zoar</hi> for <hi>Lot</hi>'s ſake, and would have done for <hi>Sodom</hi> its ſelf, had there been but Nine more ſuch as he was, to be found in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly.</hi> Our <hi>zealous</hi> Endeavours for reforming others, though they may not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43952:21"/> be effectual for the Preventing publick Calamities, yet they may be a means to preſerve us from them, or to procure for us great advantages under them. Thus were <hi>Noah,</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah</hi> preſerved, at leaſt from the extremity of thoſe publick Judgments, which by their <hi>zealous</hi> Attempts to reform the Lives of Men, they endeavoured, though unſuccesfully, to divert. But what ſhare ſoever God may think fit to give us in outward Calamities, we may be ſure of the ſupport and comfort of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience under them; a Conſcience teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying to us, that they are not the effect of any Sloth or Neglect of ours; that we did our beſt to prevent them; and that tho' we fall under them, yet we do not fall under that Wrath of God which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companies them; that all theſe things will work together for our good, who have loved and ſerved God with ſo much <hi>Zeal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly.</hi> Some perhaps may object a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe <hi>zealous</hi> Attempts to reform the Wickedneſs of the Age, that they will expoſe them to Scorn and Deriſion,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43952:22"/> to harſh Cenſures, and foul Reproaches. But had ever any great and <hi>good thing</hi> been done, if Men had always thought this, a ſufficient Excuſe for declining the attempting of it? Have not the beſt Men, and the beſt things, been always ſubject to the Scoffs and Revilings of prophane and diſſolute Men? Was there every any brave, heroical Attempt made, on the behalf of Religion, that could eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the ſpiteful Cenſures of a naughty World? But can any unjuſt Reproaches alter the nature of a good action; or make it leſs our Duty, or leſs becoming of us? Is not the approbation of our own minds, and the eſteem and love of all wiſe and good Men, and of the infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſe and good God, a ſufficient En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement againſt all the ſcurrilous Language of unreaſonable and wicked Men? Will not a ſtrong and mighty love to God make us to <hi>glory in the Croſs of Chriſt,</hi> and to <hi>rejoyce that we are counted worthy to ſuffer ſhame for his Name?</hi> A malicious Informer is indeed a Character to be abhorred; but when Informing ſignifies nothing, but Witneſſing againſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43952:22"/> the great and ſcandalous Sinners of the Age we live in, for their and the publick good, and the Glory of God, then it is a generous and honourable thing, then it is doing what all the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and all the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and our <hi>Bleſſed Lord</hi> himſelf, did before us. And <hi>if ye are reproached for ſo doing, happy are ye, for the Spirit of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and of God reſteth on you;</hi> and <hi>theſe light Afflictions, which are but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will work for you a far more exceeding and eternal weight of Glory.</hi> Why then ſhould we not ſeek, with all our Might, to <hi>affect</hi> our Hearts with <hi>Zeal</hi> in theſe matters, that with vehement Deſires, unwearied Induſtry, and Invincible Courage, we may perſue the great and <hi>good</hi> deſign, of reſtraining and reclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sinners? I proceed therefore,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5 (6)" type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly.</hi> To direct to ſome proper Conſiderations, for the inflaming our Souls with <hi>Zeal in</hi> theſe <hi>good things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> Conſider, What mighty Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations God hath laid upon you to do the utmoſt you can for him. It is <hi>in him you live, and move, and have your</hi> being. It is by his Providence that you are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43952:23"/> and by his Bounty that you are ſupplied, with all the good things you enjoy; and by the Blood of his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son, whom he freely gave for ſuch weak, and fooliſh, and provoking Sinners, that you are redeemed from Death and Hell. And can you be cold and negligent, in ſeeking to advance the Kingdom, and Honour, and Intereſt, of ſo hearty a Friend, ſo liberal a Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, ſo tender a Father, ſo good and gracious a God? Can you think of all the Wonders of the Divine Love, with cold and unaffected Hearts? Do you not bluſh to tkink, how little you have done for him, who hath done ſo much for you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly.</hi> You ſhould often ſet before you the <hi>Zeal</hi> of our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour</hi> in this matter. For this purpoſe he came down from Heaven, <hi>to ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt.</hi> He <hi>took upon him the form of a Servant, and being found in faſhion as a Man, he humbled himſelf unto death, even the death of the Croſs,</hi> that he might <hi>redeem us from iniquity, and purify to himſelf a people, zealous of good works,</hi> that he
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:43952:23"/> might <hi>destroy the works of the Devil,</hi> and reſcue the ſouls of Men out of his hands. This was the buſineſs of his Life, and the deſign of his Death. And can any thing better deſerve our <hi>Zeal,</hi> than that which he thought not unworthy of his Blood? Can we be indifferently affected to that, which our dear Redeemer valued at ſo dear a rate? Can we be better, or more honourably imployed, than in uniting our Endeavours with the Son of God, and <hi>working together with him</hi> for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of a periſhing World? Are we not concerned, that in any reſpect he ſhould live and <hi>die in vain,</hi> who lived and died for our Salvation? Can we ſtand ſtill, and make no Attempts to ſtop the growth of that, which renders his <hi>Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of none effect</hi> to Men, and <hi>destroys the Souls for whom he</hi> ſwet, and bled, and <hi>died?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly.</hi> Conſider the <hi>Zeal</hi> and Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the Enemies of this <hi>good</hi> work of reclaiming ſinful Men. How <hi>Zealous</hi> and induſtrious is the <hi>Prince of Darkneſs,</hi> in corrupting the Lives and deſtroying the Souls of Men? All his Cunning,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43952:24"/> and Strength, and Activity is imployed in this work. He is always laying his <hi>Snares,</hi> and perſuing his malicious <hi>Devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, running to and fro, and walking about, ſeeking whom he may devour.</hi> How <hi>zealous</hi> are his Agents and Miniſters, in carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the pernicious deſign of their Maſter, to advance his Kingdom, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the number of his Captives, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice Men to <hi>run with them into the ſame exceſs of Riot,</hi> and to carry them down to Hell with them? And ſhall we lie down and ſleep, and tamely ſuffer them to carry all before them? Are we not confounded with Shame to think, that they ſhould be more bold and induſtrious, in diſhonouring God, and propagating Sin, and Death, and Miſery, than we can find in our hearts to be, in promot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Glory of God, the intereſt of Piety, and the everlaſting Happineſs of Men? Is the <hi>Devil</hi> a better Maſter than <hi>God,</hi> or corrupting with ſin a better Cauſe than reſtraining Men from it? Do we ſee Men reſolutely defying the Power and Wrath of God, and boldly proceeding in their ungodly Attempts
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43952:24"/> againſt the amazing Terrors of Death and Hell? And are we diſcouraged from the moſt neceſſary, and honourable, and beneficial undertakings, for <hi>fear of men that ſhall die,</hi> or <hi>any light afflictions for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi> Is it thus we love God and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? Is it thus we anſwer the ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our Profeſſion, and the Vows we have made to our <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Redeemer?</hi> Is this our <hi>fighting manfully against Sin, the World and the</hi> Devil? Bleſſed be God that there are any ſparks of this <hi>Zeal,</hi> I have been recommending to you, reviving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us. Who can tell <hi>how great a matter</hi> this <hi>little Fire may kindle?</hi> May the <hi>Bleſſed Spirit of God,</hi> who appeared <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Fire</hi> upon the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> kindle it more and more in all our Hearts; that it may at length conſume all thoſe <hi>Tares the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emy hath ſown amongſt us,</hi> and we may henceforward bring forth ſuch Fruits unto perfection, which are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of all the care and husbandry God hath beſtowed upon us. Then we might comfortably hope, that <hi>God would be merciful unto us and bleſs us, and lift up the light of his Countenance upon us,</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:43952:25"/> and <hi>make us a praiſe in the earth,</hi> that he would be <hi>a Wall of Fire, round about us,</hi> an invincible Defence againſt all our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and <hi>the Glory in the midst of us,</hi> and that we ſhould once more ſee <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem in proſperity, and Peace upon Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at Bow-Church before the Lord Mayor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a General Faſt. On <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9. part of the 26th. and 27th. verſes.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at St. <hi>Lawrence Jewry</hi> at the Election of the Lord Mayor, 1696. On <hi>Prov. 29th.</hi> and the 2. verſe.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at the Funeral of Mr. <hi>James Lordell,</hi> March 27. 1694. On <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 13.</p>
            <p>All three by <hi>Lilly Butler</hi> Miniſter of St. <hi>Mary Aldermanbury.</hi> Sold By <hi>B. Aylmer.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:43952:25"/>
            <head>Some Books Printed for <hi>B. Aylmer</hi> at the three Pigeons in <hi>Cornhil.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SIX Sermons, <hi>viz.</hi> Of Stedfaſtneſs in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Of Family Religion. Of Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Children. Of the Advantage of an Early Piety. By his Grace <hi>John</hi> late Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Can-terbury.</hi> Price 1<hi>s.</hi> 6<hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Perſuaſive to frequent Communion in the Holy Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Alſo by his Grace. Price bound 6<hi>d.</hi> and ſticht 3 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Brief Expoſition on the Creed, the Lords Prayer, and the Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. To which is added the Doctrin of the Sacraments. By the Learned <hi>Jſaac Barrow</hi> D. D. And late Maſter of <hi>Trinity College, Cambridge.</hi> (This on the Creed never before Publiſh'd.) In 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price 4<hi>s.</hi> 6<hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Practical Diſcourſes upon the Conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of our latter End, and the Danger and miſchief of Delaying Repentance. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by Dr. <hi>Jſaac Barrow</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price 1<hi>s.</hi> 6<hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Four laſt things, <hi>viz.</hi> Death, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Heaven and Hell: practically con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered and applied, by <hi>W. Bates</hi> D. D. in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Price 2<hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43952:26"/>
            <p> Contemplations of Death and Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality. By the late Earl of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> The 15th Edition; in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price 1<hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Familiar Guide to the right and profitable Receiving of the Lords Supper. Wherein alſo the Way and Method of our Salvation is briefly and plainly declared. By <hi>Theophilus Dorrington.</hi> Price 12<hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Conference with an Anabaptiſt, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price 12<hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Theological Diſcourſe of laſt Wills and Teſtaments. Price 12<hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Seaſonable Vindication of the Bleſſed Trinity. Being an Anſwer to this Queſtion, <hi>Why do you believe the Doctrin of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?</hi> Collected from the Works of the moſt Reverend, Dr. <hi>John Tillotſon,</hi> late Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> And the Right Reverend, Dr. <hi>Edward Stillingfleet,</hi> now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter.</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price 12<hi>d.</hi> Theſe three laſt by Dr. <hi>Aſheton</hi> of <hi>Becken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Several ſmall Books againſt Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Prophaneneſs, Blaſphemy, Curſing and Swearing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo by Dr. <hi>Aſheton.</hi> Price 2<hi>d.</hi> each; but ſomething cheaper to them that give away Numbers.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
